Register of the Firing Line (Television Program) broadcast records 80040.4089238
Hoover Institution Archives
- Episode Guide, 1966-1999
  - "Politics and the Media" Guests: Shakespeare, Frank., 9 June 1970 (Item Program Number 207)
    Program details: There are few fireworks in this meeting between two old comrades in arms. However, they have a solid and productive discussion about how our information agencies operate, how they might be more effective, and--in the light of 250 State Department officials signing a protest to the Secretary of State over the Cambodian incursion--what are the different obligations of the political appointee and the career Foreign Service Officer. FS: "If a decision was undertaken by the President, which I felt very deeply in my heart and in my mind was wrong for the American people and would wreak lasting damage on the country, I think that I really would have no alternative except to resign and then publicly oppose the decision." For the career Foreign Service Officer, on the other hand, "over the next ten or twenty years there are certain to be a number of policies in any Administration that privately as a citizen he would oppose. He must support those, to the best of his ability, with the same degree of effort and professionalism as he would those he happens to support."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.207
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6141
  - "The Escalation of Student Power" Guests: Kelman, Steven.: Klein, Alexander, 1918-, 9 June 1970 (Item Program Number 208)
    Background File: Box/Folder 83: 6
    Transcript: Box/Folder 167: 17
    Program details: To discuss, as WFB puts it, "the causes and directions of student protest," we have a veteran observer and a young man who has had recent experience with the Students for a Democratic Society, "some of whose members, with only a perfunctory trace of sadness, hav[e] advised Mr. Kelman that shortly after the consummation of their revolution, it will prove quite necessary to shoot Mr. Kelman or to hang him." The conversation frequently changes direction, since it is Mr. Klein's thesis that "SDS and National Review and the Democratic Party and the Republican Party are all symptoms of a failure to really come to grips with the problems of America," whereas Mr. Kelman concentrates on SDS: "I tried above all to, instead of attributing motives, to analyze why their ideology degenerated in the way it did. Why an organization which started off saying, 'Let the people decide,' and which started off seeking certain things that I would feel are improvements in American society, degenerated into an organization whose model for America would be something like Mao Tse-tung's China."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.208
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6142
  - "The Twilight of the Presidency" Guests: Reedy, George E., 1917-, 1 July 1970 (Item Program Number 209)
    Background File: Box/Folder 83: 7
    Transcript: Box/Folder 167: 18
    Program details: A profound discussion of the Presidency, prompted by Mr. Reedy' s own experiences at Lyndon Johnson's right hand, but going back to the founding of our country ("They had no model for government other than that of monarchy.... In those days, while there was a British Parliament, ... the Prime Minister's] primary responsibility was still to the King"). GR: "When I say that [the President] loses contact [with the people], I do not mean that he is cut off from information. No.... In fact, he's smothered in information ... What I mean is that the man is not living in an environment of adversary personal relationships, which is something that is essential for maintaining psychic health.... Most of us go through the day plagued by unreasonable people - by bill collectors - " WFB: "Wives." GR: "by wives, who burst into tears because you've forgotten an anniversary ... by people that are quite likely to punch you in the nose when you step on their toe ... None of these things are pleasant. I don't regard exercise as pleasant, either. But, nevertheless, I think they are essential to an understanding of our fellow human beings, and this a President does not have."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.209
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6143
  - "The Stock Market--Ups and Downs" Guests: Smith, Adam, 1930-: Levy, Leon, 1929-, 1 July 1970 (Item Program Number 210)
    Background File: Box/Folder 83: 8
    Transcript: Box/Folder 167: 19
    Program details: Does the stock market go up and down because of real events in the outside world--government actions, the level of inflation, the earning power of particular companies at a particular time--or does it have more to do with the emotional reactions of investors? As of July 1970, the stock market, which had been strong in the early 1960s, had been lagging inflation for more than four years; as we know in hindsight, not until 1981 would the Dow-Jones Industrial Average match the high it had reached in 1965. This show offers a good, solid discussion of an elusive topic. AS: "And no matter what the next thing is that happens in the market-and there will be a next thing-it too is born to die. The day it starts to happen, its days are numbered. You simply don't know how many days there are."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.210
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6144
  - "Roosevelt: The Soldier of Freedom" Guests: Burns, James MacGregor., 28 August 1970 (Item Program Number 211)
    Background File: Box/Folder 83: 9
    Transcript: Box/Folder 167: 20
    Program details: A rich discussion with a man who is not being ironical in the title of his book (although he admits that there are ironies in it) and who is capable of holding together both the sweep and the details of World War II. In Mr. Burns's view, for example, "the decision, made for military reasons, not to open a second front in Europe in 1942 but rather to wait until 1944 wound up virtually guaranteeing Soviet hegemony over Central Europe, because by the time of Yalta we desperately wanted Soviet assistance in tackling Japan.... Russia had us just the other way around in Asia-that is, we wanted them to create the Second Front... on the mainland in Asia, in order to cut down on our casualties. And what Roosevelt did again, in his typically opportunistic, short-run, realistic way, if you will, is to pay the price [at Yalta] to get Soviet assistance against Japan, after we had failed to come to Russia's assistance in Europe."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.211
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6145
  - "International Trade" Guests: Stans, Maurice H., 1908-, 28 August 1970 (Item Program Number 212)
    Background File: Box/Folder 83: 10
    Transcript: Box/Folder 167: 21
    Program details: As Secretary of Commerce, Mr. Stans was involved, among many other things, with world trade--specifically, at this time, with trying to persuade Japan, South Korea, Taiwan, and Hong Kong to stop flooding our country with cheap textiles, and trying to persuade Congress not to respond to domestic pressure by raising tariffs and imposing import quotas. The discussion becomes quite technical at times--in terms of balance of payments and what happens to a dollar that a foreigner earns by selling goods here--but host and guest never lose us as they explore the question, as Mr. Buckley phrases it, "Why wouldn't a policy of unilateral free trade [i.e., not imposing tariffs even if others do] ultimately work out economically?"
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.212
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6146
  - "Marijuana and the Law" Guests: Kaplan, John, 1929-1989.: Kleindienst, Richard G., 1923-, 3 September 1970 (Item Program Number 213)
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168: 1
    Program details: The second Firing Line discussion of marijuana, this one an often exciting duel between a committed drug warrior and a former public prosecutor who, after working on a panel to recommend new drug legislation in California, reversed his position and came out for legalization of marijuana, on the analogy of repeal of Prohibition. Mr. Buckley starts out by asking whether "... it is possible to discuss marijuana and the law without arriving at any fixed conclusions on how harmful marijuana is." Mr. Kleindienst's first reaction is Yes; but as soon as Mr. Kaplan states that the enormous cost of criminalizing marijuana use could be justified only "if the drug were as bad as some people said it was," it becomes apparent that, in Mr. Kleindienst's words, "You have to talk about the two at the same time,... because if you took my theory that it is dangerous, then it would ... dissipate the validity of his theory."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.213
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6147
  - "How Does It Look for the Dollar?" Guests: Browne, Harry, 1933-: Janeway, Eliot., 3 September 1970 (Item Program Number 214)
    Background File: Box/Folder 83: 11
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168; 2
    Program details: Mr. Browne starts off by explaining that he isn't "advocating devaluation--he is simply looking at the world as it is" and saying that, "as an act of economic desperation," our government will have to "renege on their promise to foreign governments to pay one ounce of gold for every $35 turned in at the Treasury." (The Nixon Administration did so on August 15, 1971.) Mr. Janeway replies engagingly: "Frankly, I find myself a bit off balance being out flanked on the pessimistic side;... they pun on my name all the time and call me Calamity Janeway, and I really regard myself as the last optimist." And we're off on a high-energy discussion of the differences between domestic and international policies, or, as Mr. Janeway puts it, "the hamburger dollar available to us nationals within the sovereignty here [as against] the international dollar."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.214
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B004SQFR6E
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6148
  - "The Pueblo Story" Guests: Bucher, Lloyd M., 1927-, 10 September 1970 (Item Program Number 215)
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168: 3
    Program details: In January of 1968 North Korean boats surrounded the Pueblo, an American intelligence ship sailing in international waters, forced it to come into port in North Korea and imprisoned the crew for 11 months, and let them go only after the Johnson Administration apologized, as WFB puts it, "for doing something the United States Government wasn't guilty of doing." The often moving discussion with this man who had narrowly avoided a court martial for surrendering his ship ranges from the details of the Pueblo's, capture to general questions of intelligence collecting, to, as WFB puts it, "the business that you can only give your name, rank, and serial number" and whether that ought to be changed. LB: "I would hesitate at the present time to discuss actual recommendations ..." WFB: "Why would you be hesitant?" LB: "Because there are several hundred POWs over there in North Vietnam right now who are trying to live up to it, and with a statement that might be made by myself or any other military person, it would be used against those kids, and I wouldn't want to contribute to the problems they've already got."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.215
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6149
  - "The Supreme Court, Rule of Law, and Academic Freedom" Guests: Fellman, David, 1907-: Pritchett, C. Herman (Charles Herman), 1907-: Kort, Fred., 10 September 1970 (Item Program Number 216)
    Background File: Box/Folder 83: 12
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168: 4
    Program details: Our three guests were all attending the annual convention of the American Political Science Association, whose more traditional members were engaged in fending off a takeover by something called "A Caucus for a New Political Science." As Mr. Pritchett explains, "I think the initial concept of a professional association ... was that this was a place where you came to meet your colleagues, talk about ... our professional interests, our teaching problems, our research problems." But now the association, like the campuses where its members teach, has been politicized, and, as Mr. Fellman (whose campus had been the scene of a fatal bombing at a research laboratory) puts it, "we really haven't gotten accustomed to using the skills necessary to deal with the kind of problems the association now has." An illuminating discussion among men fighting to maintain standards of intellectual discipline against the bomb throwers.
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.216
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6150
  - "Why Are They Afraid of Bach?" Guests: Tureck, Rosalyn., 28 September 1970 (Item Program Number 217)
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168: 5
    Program details: A lovely show with the keyboard artist who, according to one reviewer, is "to Bach what Marilyn Monroe is to movies." The question before the house is whether young rock fans can be shown that Bach is not dry and academic; Miss Tureck illustrates her points superbly at the keyboard, but, as her engagement with the young panelists demonstrates, she is as much at home with words as with her own craft. Miss Tureck, to panelist Phil Ardery: "I would like to ask you a question, and that is, do you feel when you hear a composer playing his own music, do you feel he's creating it on the spot? Is this the excitement that you feel from him?" PA: "It's what I feel when I go to concerts. I go to a Grateful Dead concert and look at Jerry Garcia improvise on his guitar and listen with my ears to the sounds he gets and it's different every time I hear him ..."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.217
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6151
  - "The Middle East" Guests: Eban, Abba Solomon, 1915-2002., 28 September 1970 (Item Program Number 218)
    Background File: Box/Folder 84: 1
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168: 6
    Program details: Minutes before the taping began, a messenger arrived to tell Mr. Eban that Gamal Abdel Nasser-Israel's principal tormentor for 14 years-was dead. As Mr. Buckley puts it, "Such is the pace of events in the Middle East that no conversation held about it on Monday appears to be relevant on Tuesday ... On the other hand, the causes of the tension do not change from day to day." The refugee camps are the main focus of discussion with this man who had made an indelible imprint with his internationally televised UN speech on the occasion of the Six-Day War. AE: "We have no guilt ... for that problem; not at all. We have responsibility with the rest of the international community. So, I am responsible in the measure that you are responsible, and we must all do what we can. But guilt, certainly not. Guilt lies with the governments who declared that war" (against Israel, in 1948).
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.218
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6152
  - "Between Two Ages: America's Role in the Technetronic Era" Guests: Brzezinski, Zbigniew K., 1928-, 8 October 1970 (Item Program Number 219)
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168: 7
    Program details: "Technetronic" being, as WFB explains, "a simple agglutination of 'technological' and 'electronic'." It is Mr. Brzezinski's thesis that the industrial age, "which, itself, produced many strains and tensions, did lead after a time to a number of coherent ideas as to how, more or less, to organize society, how to conduct international politics." But now, as we enter the "technetronic age," the new phenomena-but especially "the impact of modern communications, of modern means of calculations, of modern means of interacting"-have led to the breakdown of "established values, established institutions." And so we're off on a rich and, as it turns out, prophetic discussion of this "messy, congested, chaotic, fragmented, barely structured, partially orderly, partially disorderly" transition.
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.219
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6153
  - "Chile and the Future of South America" Guests: Geyer, Georgie Anne, 1935-: Rodman, Selden, 1909-, 8 October 1970 (Item Program Number 220)
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168: 8
    Program details: Chile, as Mr. Buckley sets the scene, is "in the news as perhaps the first state that will have voted itself into Communism. Mr. Allende is designated as the instrument for the scheduled totalitarianization of the state." Why Chile? Why this country where just six years earlier, as Miss Geyer tells it, "when Frei was elected ... there was a tremendously heady atmosphere ... a spontaneous outpouring of simple joy and relief on the part of the Chilean people that somehow they had voted for a reformist government without a Marxist government"? This proves to be an extremely rich discussion with two close observers of Latin America, explaining such matters as why there has to be, in Miss Geyer's phrase, "a conscious redistribution of wealth": "Largely because of the Spanish characteristics ... You have an economic system that is only an extension of family groups.... There is not much way for the aggressive young man to work in because he can't get credit; the banks are controlled by one family group-the credit goes to the people of that family."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.220
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6154
  - "Africa and Colonialism" Guests: Huxley, Elspeth Joscelin Grant, 1907-1997., 20 October 1970 (Item Program Number 221)
    Background File: Box/Folder 84: 2
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168: 9
    Program details: Mrs. Huxley, who had been raised in Kenya, was highly regarded as an observer of her own country and of Africa generally. This fascinating conversation explores the whole subject of decolonialization, including the limitations of Western democracy in a region accustomed to other methods of decision-making, and the question of how a colonial power should go about letting go. EH: "There does come a point when you've got to choose. Either you say, 'We'll wait for an ideal situation, when more people have had time to graduate from universities and there are more skilled people equipped to takeover the reins of government.' You can do this. Or you can say, 'That is worse...because it involves shooting a lot of people.' Then there is the question of any kind of future based on good will. If you leave in an atmosphere of bloodshed and violence, you can't expect to attain what you hope to be a commonwealth."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.221
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B004VGGY7M
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6155
  - "Britain's Most Controversial MP" Guests: Powell, J. Enoch (John Enoch), 1912-1998., 20 October 1970 (Item Program Number 222)
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168: 10
    Program details: "Since last appearing on this program," Mr. Buckley begins, "Enoch Powell has made fresh-and very bitter-enemies.... [He] repeated his warnings that England would be overwhelmed by colored immigrants and added the suggestion that subversive forces in England were arguing subtly for an end to the British way of life." And we're off on a glorious ride with Britain's vieillard terrible. WFB: "Why do they say about you that you have become the McCarthyite? ..." EP: "I never understand-" WFB: "Did you think to ask?" EP: "I never understand these American- I didn't ask Anthony Lewis, no; I wouldn't touch him with a barge pole." WFB: "Would you touch the editors of the Guardian, or the Telegraph and the Times, with a barge pole?" EP: "I don't think the Telegraph probably applies this expression to me. The Times, as you probably know, has become our leading Maoist daily. And so you go to the Times in order to find examples of the very things I'm talking about." WFB: "Are you using a metaphor?" EP: "Why no. No, I'm quite serious. Indeed, perhaps-" WFB: "Is one of your fields of expertise the libel law? I hope?"
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.222
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6156
  - "In Defense of Practical Socialism" Guests: Crossman, R. H. S. (Richard Howard Stafford), 1907-1974., 21 October 1970 (Item Program Number 223)
    Background File: Box/Folder 84: 3
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168: 11
    Program details: A splendid session with the man regarded, as WFB puts it, "as the most reliable exegete of practical socialism, if one will permit the oxymoron." The discussion begins with the Wilson government's failure to reduce, as Mr. Grossman puts it, "the gap between the standard of living of the poor and the not-so-poor," given other problems such as the balance of payments; and goes back and forth between the practical and the theoretical. WFB: "What do you make of the criticism ... that socialism is in a sense an exercise in utopianism, and the balance of payments, mutatis mutandis, is always going to stand in the way of executing socialism. If it isn't that, it's going to be inflation, or it's going to be a lack of-" RC: "Yes. Well, you put it that way; I'll put it another way. I think socialism is the belief in the impossible. But then, you see, every good ideal is a belief in the impossible. Remember when he said, 'Credo quia impossibile'-Tertullian, the Christian, he said, 'I believe because it is impossible.' Now this is something I've always thought was the essential about a radical."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.223
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6157
  - "Three British Journalists Question WFB" Guests: Palmer, John, 1930-: Steele, Jonathan.: Malcolm, Derrick., 21 October 1970 (Item Program Number 224)
    Transcript: Box/Folder 168: 12